Hello, good afternoon everybody. Uh this
is Dominic Zerlo with the New Mexico
Department of Health and uh our uh the
chair for this meeting Desba is uh
actually going to be joining here in
just a few moments. She is running into
uh just a little bit of issues logging
in. So we're working in getting that
resolved. Um, in the meantime, um, what
I will, uh, just wanted to go over is
that this meeting is for the medical
psilocybin program, the equity, access,
and cultural considerations committee.
Uh, and the chair of it is Dezba and
again, she'll be joining us here in just
a moment. Um and uh my understanding is
how she has been working and running
these meetings these this particular
meeting is as more of a listening
session because she wants to hear uh and
we want to hear from people who have
concerns, comments, uh constructive
ideas and different things uh with
regard to um the medical psilocybin and
especially with regard to access,
equity, and other cultural
considerations. This meeting is being
recorded and uh once the meeting has
concluded, uh it does take us a few
business days to get these up on our
website, but they will be put onto our
website. Um if you have uh questions
about other committees, for example, if
you have not been able to join those
other meetings that have occurred, the
same is true for those. What we do ask
again is it can take a few business days
for those meetings and those recordings
of those meetings to be up on the
website. Um but they are and they will
be available usually within about five
business days. Sometimes it takes a
little bit longer. Please just be
patient. Our IT team at the Department
of Health does their best to be able to
get those up there, but it does
sometimes take a little bit of time. Um,
and with that in mind, um, we do have a
few, uh, or for this meeting, when
individuals are getting ready to speak,
when we're ready to ask for that, we'll
ask people to raise their hands and then
once individuals have raised their
hands, what we will go ahead and do is
we will call on order for those
individuals and then you will be able to
speak at that time. Um, when we do call
on you, we will have unmuted you from
our end, but you will need to unmute
yourself on your end. And I will be
putting up instructions here in just a
moment on how to do that. But
essentially, it is uh to raise your
hand, just go to the upper portion of
the team's window, and there is a little
hand icon there that says raise and then
you can go ahead and actually raise your
hand. Um and then as far as to speak
once we unmute you then you will be able
to um uh at that point you will be able
to uh unmute your line and the way you
do that is just click on the mic button.
Please make sure that your microphone is
one of a microphone that is working.
Sometimes we have had where people have
had headphones uh that are connected but
are in another room or in another area
and so they have not been able to speak
at that point. Um however uh just check
on that aspect. Um and then um with
regard to uh with regard to um if you're
on a phone it is we'll we'll put that
information on up and I do see in the
chat that there is someone who said they
cannot hear. Are there other individuals
who can? If one or two people can just
put in the chat, can you hear us or that
way we can look and see if it is just
for that one individual or other people?
Oh, here we go. Okay, great. Thank you,
James and Robert. Uh, thank you very
much. I appreciate No one other people
don't need to say they can hear. We'll
get that here in just a moment. Uh, so
thank you very much. I appreciate that.
actually tells me everybody is being not
only can hear but very respons
responsive. So, we thank you for that.
For a few people who were a little bit
late in joining on in, Desba is joining
us. Uh she is working on getting
everything set on up and so uh will be
joining us here shortly in just a
moment. In the meantime, again, what
we're just talking about is the fact
that this is really more of a listening
session. And uh that once we are able to
start uh with regard to public comment
and to hear from people, what we will go
ahead and do is we will open it up, have
people raise their hands, and then from
that point, we will unmute you on our
end. You'll just have to unmute yourself
on your end, and then you'll be able to
speak.
And with that, Desba, have you Oh, give
me just a moment.
>> Hi. Sorry for the technical
difficulties.
>> You are there, Despot. And we can hear
you now. So that is perfect. I did, just
so you're aware, I did an introduction
that this is as a listening session and
uh how people can actually hear. So if
you'd like to introduce yourself and
your thoughts, ideas and then uh it is
your meeting.
>> All right. Thank you. Y Desba um thank
you all for being here. Sorry for the
delay. Um technology is not my friend
right now. Um so anyways, thank you
Dominic for um doing the introductions
for I'm I'm both on my computer and on
my phone. There's that's that's the way
it is right now. Um, so that's why
you're seeing my name double. And it's
good to see a bunch of James, I see that
you're here. Um, any other Brett, I also
see that you're here as well. Um, let's
see some other people. Some new people.
Marina here. Richard. Um, let's see.
Mer. Okay, awesome. Denali, great. So
this is um basically what I had wanted
to just get like more people involved in
understanding like what are the concerns
um for this specific committee for
equity, access and cultural
considerations. It is a huge broad um
kind of topic and so um
you know I guess just as many people who
might have something and dying to say
something um please do. Initially what I
had um I don't think that the video and
the minutes have been posted just yet uh
from the last session um but basically
you know what I consider as far as I
have an obligation as the Native
American component of the advisory board
is to ensure that we do have um access
to that cultural um uh contribution. So
we are going to be doing I am all of us
with your contacts with all the hard
work that everyone has been doing really
trying to get that um input as to what
you know the tribes may or may need.
It's complicated. There's federal
regulations New Mexico state tribal
sovereignty. It's a really huge um
converging con confluence of of all of
these governance and what does that look
like? But not only that, broadly, you
know, ind in indigenous ancestral wisdom
to me is something that has been here
prior to, you know, even human
existence. That is where we're kind of
meeting the mushroom essentially. Um,
and what does that look like? And I feel
that as at least for my part, you know,
that's not something that is necessarily
I'm lifting indigenous wisdom and
ancestral wisdom on my own. that it is
actually up to all of us in the board
and as a community to really kind of
make sure that we are listening to the
medicine in the sense of how are we
going to um bring back the you know what
governance is when it comes to
regulation when it comes to safety when
it comes to frameworks um we are only
looking at psilocybin we are not looking
at other types of of psychedelic
medicine but that is you know something
that might be in the back of our mind
and something that at a very close to
our heart especially when we're talking
about plant medicine and ancestral
wisdom. This is a short session and
again I apologize for the fact that it
was um technical difficulties on my part
but if there's anybody who is already
dying to speak please do so. Um very
very very um
you know you don't have to really do too
much of an introduction. Um we are going
to understand that there are agendas um
as far as like where your platform is
you know where you are at. We are going
to be looking at people or listening to
people who are from outside of New
Mexico, outside other organizations, but
we are strictly also looking at how this
affects New Mexican citizens and those
that um live, work, and cultivate here.
So, there's any other questions for me
specifically, go ahead. But I would
actually just really like if there's
anyone who has um a specific concern
that they wanted to bring up and bring
to the forefront.
We'll we'll kind of keep it to about
three minutes maybe just so I kind of
kind of short and sweet.
I think I see who is it.
>> So we have Shane there.
>> Yep.
>> Shane have on uh I have uh un minted
you. So you just have to manually uh go
up there and press un speak.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Um, so just off the top of my
head, um, how are we defining
the the equity portion of this? Um, as
far as or you know, um, because equity
seems to be a word that has I'm an older
guy, so um, over the last 10 years, the
definition has changed somewhat, it
seems like. So I want to understand what
how you're defining equity here.
>> Okay.
Um, equity is just being able that
across as far as I understand it is just
across the board. It's not necessar it
it's it could be geographical locations.
That's another thing that we're looking
at. In the last session, we were looking
at teaalth and how that might be
implemented in providing that equity.
You know, there's rural um locations. I
grew up in northern New Mexico. Um there
are people who have um interest you know
for providing to people in Mora or other
rural communities. Um it could be
financial um in terms of financial
cultural um but being able to provide
uh and and those are the things that we
are going to look at. What are those
definitions specifically? we might be
borrowing language from other places um
from other parts of the department or
other things that are in place. Um so
those can be implemented into it, but
that's part of what we're looking at is
what are these what what is going to
define that? So that is a good question.
What is what is that going to look like?
And that's kind of where we're coming
in. If there's something already in
place, we might use that as a
definition. broadly. It could be um
uh what what is it that looks like for
for New Mexicans at this at this point?
Someone did like a financial
what is what is the uh poverty line
right now? Someone redid this and found
out it's not just food, shelter, and uh
I can't remember what the third one is
anymore. You know, it's it the cost of
living is no longer, you know, $50,000.
It's like $132,000
nationwide that that's the poverty line
because of health insurance, because of
all these other other things that we
have to pay for. So, that is a good
question. What is that? What is it
really going to be defined?
>> Right? Because we, you know, um talking
about in doing some research, I've done
a lot of research. I've researched
Oregon and Colorado on this and they've
got it wrong there. Um it's it's uh way
too expensive for the
patient um or the um
person that's that's seeking healing.
Um and I would like to see New Mexico
get that part right and not make this a
money grab. Yes, money has to be made
right. I'm a I I understand capitalism,
but when it becomes
too expensive for the people that need
it the most, which um which, you know,
we've got two very heavily
um hit communities by opiate addictions
and maybe more. I know of two that they
about nationally quite a bit and that's
Espanola and Tal.
Um,
if it's $5 $10,000 for a
to get a treatment or you know, it's
that's too expensive. $1,000 is too
expensive, right? For for some of these
people that are at the end of their rope
and and and definitely if they had if
they had $1,000, they wouldn't be Well,
let's just put it this way. I have a lot
of history with drug addiction and and
most drug addicts ain't won't be able to
come up with $1,000 to get treatment. We
need to figure out a way that um because
insurance probably is not going to pay
for this for a long time.
Um
we'll see what happens there. But we've
got to get this working at a at a
affordable level for the people that
need it the most. And I'm probably over
my three minutes, so I'll give it back
to you. Thank you. Appreciate. Yes.
Saw someone else who had a hand up. But
then
>> have another question by Oh, a hand
raised by Dan. Uh Dan, I have allowed
your mic. If you could please unmute
yourself and begin to speak.
>> Hello. Um wanted to say thank you for
allowing me to be here and um I am
Daniel Houston from uh Portland, Oregon.
I own Rose City Laboratories, the first
and only licensed laboratory in the
state. Um, I agree with that last person
that uh Oregon and Colorado
uh have some things wrong. um it's not
affordable and uh you know I I don't
mind sharing but uh I we're a
environmental laboratory and a cannabis
laboratory also which is the only reason
that I'm able to afford to be able to
test for the psilocybin industry. I do
it because it's a passion of mine and
I'm here because I hope and pray that
other people other states will listen
and try to do it right and better. Um, I
believe that
probably you guys should try to keep any
outside companies outside including um,
and this isn't going to be popular, but
even including uh um, training facil
training facilities, schools, uh, keep
that all in in your state. Um,
there's been so many things going wrong.
Uh back in July, I checked my books just
to see how much money I had made for
testing for the psilocybin industry and
it's constantly going down because
people don't need continuing treatments
and people are doing larger batches. So,
back in July, I had only done like
$11,000 in sales and for that industry.
And out of that $11,000, I have to pay
$10,000 for a uh renewal license, which
is way too much. So, I had to raise my
prices 90%.
Um,
everybody's going to still pay it and
everybody's going to still do it. Um,
but it, you know, at the end of
December, uh, I had done $25,000 in
sales.
Uh, a company can't survive on that. It
has to be affordable. You have to keep
companies in New Mexico,
allow them to do it. Don't allow outside
companies to come in. limit the number
of training facilities because honestly
you're gonna run into a brick wall where
you're gonna have so many people trained
because everybody's excited but yet
there's not going to be enough work for
everybody. So not everybody's going to
be able to renew their license. Um,
I just really would like to see um, you
know, Oregon and Colorado allow people,
you know, we talk about equity, we talk
about indigenous here in Oregon, but yet
I don't see them being serviced. Um, you
can't go to a tribal
property or facility and do it because
there's no facilities there. you should
be allowed to, you know, do it in homes
for people that are dying.
Um, and a lot of that's going to reduce
a lot of the overhead and the costs by
allowing the freedom. Sorry, I'm
probably over my limit. Um, I'll shut
up. If you guys have any questions, I'll
stay on, but it's it's tough here and
the industry here is collapsing.
Um, just thought I'd let you guys know.
Thank you.
>> Appreciate it, Dan. And then before you
decide to to uh to go off, um we do have
other committees and then I'm sure that
anybody else who is not here would be
interested in even hearing your input,
your your um what you have to say. We
have of end of life care also for anyone
else who's listening. End of life care
is coming up I think tomorrow at 3 p.m.
We have um propagation committees,
training and education is as further on
after at the end of the month. So keep a
lookout for the Department of Health and
we I mean at least I speak for myself
and I know that I we do need this input
from other people and we do need to have
more of a conversation and a discussion
and you know we're looking for this
input. We're looking for what you have
to say about what's not working and what
has worked because we do want to get it
more right as we proceed in this and we
have such an a responsibility to not
also just our citizens here in New
Mexico but for the whole of you know our
the of humanity I really feel um to to
be Santa Fe woo woo we have a
responsibility to the whole of humanity
to work to try to meet the what the
medicine wants us to do as as a as a
community as a governance and so I
appreciate your insight. Thank you.
>> Um who else?
>> Lisa Ginsburg. Uh I have allowed your
mic. Uh you may now unmute and begin to
speak.
>> Hello. Uh hi everyone. Um thank you so
much for your time and for all your work
um putting this together. Um I
appreciate the notes that been shared
previously with other speakers. I um
personally believe in a open market and
equity means access to everyone. And I
believe that restricting
this access only for the citizens would
limit tremendously the opportunity to
learn from the best minds from research
centers from John Hopkins, NYU because a
lot of training programs bring a wealth
of knowledge. um that already exists. Uh
I also think that opening access will
drive prices down. Um we see a big slow
down in Oregon. Colorado was still
trying to understand what's happening
there. Uh and I think that's natural for
new emerging industries. However,
opening access will create more
opportunities. And I also
really happy to see that New Mexico is
launching a medical model that would
allow practitioners, medical
practitioners provide this medicines to
um the patients, the clients, uh which
is very different from Oregon and
Colorado. for that. I definitely believe
that this practitioner should have
access to the best education possible
that might not exist currently in New
Mexico. Um, and of course, the more
practitioners we have licensed,
especially practitioners partially why
we see the slowdown in Colorado and
Oregon is because it's a recreational
model. So, a lot of people entering this
system for the wrong reasons. People
with very poor education coming in
thinking they're going to make a lot of
money providing psilocybin to their
clients. It's not the case. If we allow
licensed therapists provide this to
their clients, they already have
database of clients. They already know
what they're doing. So, for one, they
can provide better services. For two,
the more trained practitioners we have,
nurses, therapists, doctors, the better
it is for the clients. So, I believe we
should create accessible program
that can potentially drive prices down,
but the only way to drive prices down is
by creating more practitioners. So,
thank you so much. I appreciate your
work. And that's all I want to say.
>> Thank you.
All
right. Is there anybody else who
wanted to say James?
Thank James.
>> Hi. Can you guys hear me?
>> Wonderful. My name is James and I'm from
Arizona. It's a pleasure to be with you
all and thank you Desba for hosting this
meeting. Um my curiosity lie with um
Native American tribal leaders and
practitioners that utilize pote in their
ceremony. And I think it's uh invaluable
wisdom to look to them because they
truly understand set and setting amongst
indigenous um I should say um
experiences.
And so I think it would be really good
for this committee to um look to tribal
leaders and obtain kind of their
perspectives because I think it is
something that is going to be really
implementable especially with the 219 uh
bill. So thank you very much for
listening and understanding.
>> Thank you James.
There anyone else who
wants to
chime in here? No. No. Okay.
Yeah. So, from the people that have
spoken up, um, you know, what I'm
looking at too is I know that's
listening isn't so much like getting
down to business and I totally
understand that. Um, and it's just like
a small group. Um it will be more
formalized in in the coming meetings
that we do have figuring out like what
is the actual structure trying to get
through a lot of this. Um and part part
of like why it's just kind of listening.
I just wanted to hear like who who who's
kind of out there actually listening in
on what's going on here. Um it's kind of
hoping to get flooded with a lot of
people um wanting to kind of chime in
and give their um their input. But as
far as like tribal um like I had
mentioned before um at least in my
understanding that there are grassroots
uh organizations and networks that are
trying to reach out and do education
outreach when it comes to uh getting
into the PBLO especially here it's
mostly PBLO um and then there's a patch
in the Navajo Nation it gets a little
bit trickier I think when it comes to
specifically like Navajo which crosses
three different states. Um, and so to me
trying to make sure that understand like
what does tribal governance look like
when we're talking about New Mexico
state and then also with any federal
regulations and or treaty um treaties
that are already in place such as taking
care of the Native Americans through um
IHS and so forth. Um but really
understanding how
those what we're trying to do here
bridges into that. I know we have a
tribal liaison um with the department of
health um already in place um and then
also different uh tribal health
practitioners um
so Dominic did you have your hand up?
Yeah, Despa I just one thing I wanted to
add in is because you did mention about
our tribal liaison here at DO and one of
the things that we've been speaking with
them regarding is setting up a meeting
specifically for the Native American
tribes, PBLO and nations. um so that uh
to be a safe and inviting place for
individuals from those communities to be
able to come and express and to be able
to do so in in a in a much more involved
way hopefully. And so we're working on
that. The one issue we of course have
run into as many people on this call
know is that's difficult to arrange
during the legislative session which
starts very shortly. And so we're trying
to see when and where we can do that.
Once it is set up um it will be uh once
the meeting has completed uh we will
have information about that but it will
be an invitation to the tribes PBLO and
nations to be able to participate and
join in and ensure that we're hearing
from as many different communities and
people as possible. So just wanted to
make sure people know about that. We've
been talking about it for a bit if but
it unfortunately uh just with as many
different pieces as are involved it
takes a little while to get set up.
>> Yes, exactly. That's a good point to um
to make Dominic because for anyone who
is listening and is not very aware and
I'm also learning this as well at this
time of year at just yesterday a lot of
the PBLO did um go through the
ceremonies of I guess installing or you
know the changing of the colors for the
different tribes governors. Um so it's
king's day is yesterday so they did a
lot of ceremonies like in TAS in Santa
Domingo and that's when the govern then
they change every year. So that's
another you know added challenge of you
know getting everyone on the same page.
Um so it's not as if things are not
happening for anyone who's like really
really excited and worried and you know
what about the tribes. It's just tribal
governance. It's you know it's not just
necessarily all what it's it's to the
best of what we can do. Um and so all
the PBLO are changing um every year.
That's another thing. Um, and so then
also again, Navajo Nation, completely
different thing, three different states.
What does that look like? So, what I'm
hoping for, and again, it's sorry I jump
around a lot, but um is the flexibility
of what that equity and access and
cultural considerations actually really
looks like in sense of what is
established within the regulations of
New Mexico, that the access is friendly
as to what Dominic was saying, friendly,
accessible, that there is education and
outreach available to um and for the
liaison or however we implement this for
the provos should they choose as to be a
part of their governance right that's
one level the other level which is what
I mentioned is the grassroots level
where a lot of people are working in um
on their own
valition to reach out into and um and
have that education have that outreach
um and so those are also the people that
I feel like because that's more that
that's less governance it's more
personal. Let's just put it that way. Um
it that might be a way to marry the two
or at least have some kind of um
confluence with with with the effort,
right? Um and I feel like that's what
the access for. Um kind of back to the
first question like what is equity? And
I know that Lisa explained, you know,
it's for everyone and I think that is
true. The only reason why it's within
the the constraints of New Mexico is
because borders.
Um, and of course, you know, what does
that look like? And you know, New Mexico
is on the forefront of a lot of things.
Um, we've got lots, we take care of our
citizens to the best of our ability, I
feel. Um, and I feel uh when it comes to
healthcare, um, and there are a lot of
things that we're lacking, but I feel
like this is definitely one of the ways
in which we can as this as a community
of New Mexico pull our own people up by
supporting, wrapping around and and
giving that support through access to
this medicine. Um, I think I see Ellie
L. buyers
who has their hand up.
>> Perfect.
>> Thank you. Hi. Nice to meet everybody.
My name is L. I'm a social worker. I'm
based in New York City, but I'm
originally from New Mexico. And
something that comes up for me first and
foremost when thinking about access and
equity is education. um out here in my
practice, I work primarily with bipok
populations and something that I notice
um is like a resistance to ancestral
medicines and I think that that's
largely because of coloniality and so
education is I think a really important
part of this conversation and a really
big part of decolonial work um as well
because we have to do we have to
implement a lot of like unteing the
propaganda around these medicines um for
people to want to access them or feel
safe accessing them. Um and yeah, I
think some another point that someone
else uh brought up um when they were
talking about like the recreational
model versus the medical model. Um I
think that that's a really strong point.
Um especially because um in western
society as it stands currently um you
know and big pharma and its dominance um
most people especially marginalized
communities have access to treatment and
to medicine through services like ERS.
And so, um, they're not necessarily in
spaces or have access to spaces where
it's like private clinical practice or
groups. Um, and so I think it's really
important to like work through when
we're talking about how to make access
more possible for these communities. I
think it's important to acknowledge what
is like dominant and popular and
accessible um, now and work through that
angle, if that makes sense. Um, I hope
that all of those points make sense. I
might not be as articulate as everybody
else. Um, but yeah, I just wanted to
share those points.
>> No, thank you. Um, El, before we get to
Meredith, just really quickly when
you're pointing out the recreational
model versus the medical model and then
kind of undoing the colonial systems, I
think that's really important to that to
that. Um, the thing that comes to mind
is, you know, at first they took away
education from Native Americans and, you
know, and we were forced to assimilate
to, you know, white colonial standards,
right? And because we're stupid. Um, and
then now it's just like, well, we're
fighting back based on the terms and the
metrics that were imposed on us. We're
getting degrees as lawyers and medical,
etc., etc. So working through that
model, I feel what you're saying is, you
know, what is what is the dominant thing
here and when it becomes something
that's um safe to use um through the
medical and that's kind of the thing
that we're talking about. Some people
are on the side of we need access to
outdoors, this needs to be done in an
environment that is, you know, outside,
etc. And then but we have some people
who would feel that's too much and you
know we have to meet the person and the
medicine what it's what it's it's
calling for really personal off-the-wall
analogy. I can snorkel in the ocean. I'm
fine. Put me in a pool. I can't do it
for some reason. So, I get what you're
saying as far as use whatever it is that
we have, the tools that are available to
us because not everybody is the same and
we really need to meet the person and
provide the environment that is most
conducive to a person's healing
regardless of where their background is.
Um and then also with in mind the
colonial systems that um working working
and using the colonial systems um to to
further our own people which I feel is
partially the reason why we have the
governance um and in New Mexico
regulations
if that also makes sense to anybody. Um,
Meredith,
>> hi. Um, I was curious as to whether or
not there's been any conversations about
um, uh, pro people on probation and how
to get them access to this medicine. Um,
and then maybe further down the line is
like people who are currently
incarcerated. um we have a lot of the
population an large incarcerated
population in New Mexico and who might
very much benefit from access to these
medicines. So um within this
conversation of equity kind of thinking
about people who are often um shunted to
the sidelines of our communities uh who
would really really benefit from the
access. I was just curious if that's
been in the conversation at all. No,
Meredith. So far, you're the first
person. Um, and I feel like it would
really work with the recidivis
recidivism. Um, Dominic, I think, has
something to say on that.
>> Yeah, it it hasn't come up in these
meetings, but we've actually been
exploring that. There are some issues
with um with regard to the requirements
of probation or parole. Um, and then of
course when individuals are
incarcerated, including that they cannot
be utilizing substances that are
schedule one. And so those are some
barriers that are going to need to be
resolved. Um, and just to kind of give
an idea, those are some things that we
have worked through previously with
regard to cannabis as an example. And so
I actually have hoped that we'll be able
to do that, but that's a much longer
process. Um it has been brought up uh
again as far as discussions internally
and about how do we reach those
individuals because we have a lot of
programs at the Department of Health
that work with incarcerated individuals
and uh we do want to make sure that we
can uh access it. And as was just put in
the chat, the current law does not
prohibit it. It's really about uh as far
as for people who are on probation
parole, it's really about the other
requirements that there may be based
upon um other uh you know with them
being on probation and utilizing
substances. So we have to work through
those and again we're pretty um pretty
confident that we'll be able to do that
but it may take some time.
>> Thank you Dominic.
We we have a question here from Dan, I
believe. Or is it Meredith again?
Actually, I forgot to lower your hand. I
apologize.
Uh, okay,
Dan. You go ahead.
Um, I just wanted to bring up, I wasn't
sure if the health department there,
everybody is aware that um, the DEA
recently uh, put out a memo asking for
an increase in psilocybin production.
Um,
so I just wanted to throw that out
there. Um, I think the government is the
federal government is uh, going to be a
lot more relaxed moving forward.
I did not see that memo. It doesn't
surprise me though.
>> Thank you, Denali.
>> We have another point.
You may unmute. Go ahead.
>> Hi everyone. Um, grateful to Desba for
your leadership and the department uh
for convening. Um, my name is Denali. I
am the director of strategic support for
the healing advocacy fund which is a
nonprofit that supports um psychedelic
therapies and specifically the state
regulated access programs. I'm based in
Los Cusus. Just a couple of things as
this uh discussion rolls on. I am really
grateful to hear um energy and
excitement about engaging people in
custody, whether that's in prison or on
probation and parole. And I appreciate
Jeff's um uh acknowledgement of the
statutory protection. I'd say it goes
farther than doesn't prohibit them from
participating, but the statute actually
protects people who are on probation and
parole. So there's there's a section
that says that they cannot people who
are on probation and parole cannot but
be penalized um whether that's violation
of parole or anything else uh for their
participation in the therapeutic
program. So I'm really grateful to the
legislative leadership that made that um
made sure that that's a part of it.
There's the there's the statute and the
protection. So grateful for that. Um, a
couple of things and if I go too long,
just interrupt me, Desba, um, or anyone
else. But I
I know that a really important equity
question early on for the department and
for and for the advisory board is going
to be um developing the list of approved
clinicians. I don't know that in the um
creation of the subcommittees that was
specifically within this within the
scope of any and maybe that's best it's
best to be left to the full advisory
board to make those recommendations to
the department of health. But I think
that that's an early important question
for the advisory board to be considering
and of course want to see that list to
be as uh expansive as possible
especially including peer support
workers, community health workers that
are already integrated into our
healthcare continuum and those services
are already reimburseable and recognized
under state Medicaid also traditional
healers. Um
um
let's see. I took a couple of other
notes. Oh, there was there was some
discussion um too about insurance and
this question of whether um you know
we're going to be able to as as a major
barrier to access um and equity. Um I I
think we're really lucky to be in New
Mexico um where we have a healthc care
authority that is our state Medicaid
office that um has demonstrated, you
know, a true commitment to finding a way
to make this work. Of course, there's
there's not going to be until there
until and if there is FDA approval,
there won't be a way for this for the
state um to cover uh the actual
medicine. But um there seems to be a lot
of energy and creativity in thinking
about the ways that um that we can cover
all of the other parts of the care model
which is most of the care model. Um
and um on that I think the way to make
the um to make the money that right. So
we have to commit to insurability and
accessibility and supporting the
healthcare authority to make sure that
they have what they need to develop um
that coverage and then be the model for
commercial insurance to cover. Um and
then right for the piece that is not um
minuscule but right a part of the care
model that won't be able to be covered
that's where you know the equity fund
that the that the bill created um plays
a really important role. I've mentioned
this before and I'll mention it again.
Um I I'm a little concerned that the
health the funding of the equity fund um
that that timeline wasn't pulled in when
we pulled in the timeline for the
program. And so if we are going to be
with moving towards a goal of seeing
patients in December, we need also to
have money to pay for that treatment.
And um I know it's not a part of it
wasn't a part of the governor's budget.
The legislative finance committee um
released their budget today and it also
was not a part of that budget. That
doesn't mean it's not going to happen,
but it does mean we have to work to make
it happen. And so um I'm committed to
that. I know there are others here who
are, but just want to continue to to be
monitoring the funding of the equity
fund so that we can actually pay for
treatment um when we set up the program.
>> And I think that's
>> and Danelli, so that last part when
you're talking about so the when you're
saying that there was no money for the
budget like even to get it when we're
talking equity, right? uh I guess to
oversimplify it is that when when we
roll this out and we like okay you know
green light
that there that the potential is
potential and not the you know the hope
is there is but the potential is that
the people who may need it most let's
say example is Espanola area Chimayo
area etc wherever um the people that are
working with it are really hoping for
this medicine to be able to help them.
They might be the ones losing out
because there's no money in the budget
for them.
>> Um, so, so
yeah, I think so. So, the
team created
>> Yeah. Can I can I respond? Okay. And
then maybe Dominic, I if you want to
jump in. Um but SB 219 created an equity
fund which is to provide um you know
whether that is a scholarship in total
for treatment or partial funding you
know the eligibility is to be determined
and that's part of what do um with the
help of the advisory board I think we'll
we'll be doing over this next year but
right there's no there's no there's not
much decision to be made if the fund
hasn't been funded and so there's right
now the fund is created by the law but
there's no money in the fund. So, the
legislature has to act to um to actually
put money into that fund so that it can
be distributed to patients in need.
>> Yeah.
Great. All right. Thank you for your
input on that. Um
I don't think there's anybody else who
has their hand raised. And so I just
want to we're kind of closing in on the
last little bit of time. Thank you all
for, you know, having the patience to
listen and to speak. I know it's a
little nerve-wracking. Jeff, did you
And here's a couple of things and then
the future meetings for anybody else,
you know, whether it's to call me out on
something that I've misspoke about.
Totally. I'm I'm here to learn just as
much. I want to acknowledge like all of
the hard work that everybody has already
done with all of that they're doing. Um,
and um, let's see. I'm going to read
this out loud. Hi, this is from uh
Senator Seinborn. Uh we'll be working
hard this session to get funding for the
equity fund and definitely encourage you
to contact your legislator legislators
to ask for their support. All right. So,
our um New Mexico legislator legislation
is starting January 20th. Um, we do have
a social calendar that I am aware of
that is being put up on their state
website where they have the different
um, days for different events that are
happening. But, um, you know, for anyone
who does manage to make it up here to
Santa Fe, it would be great to go say hi
to the senators and tell them how
important this is if you haven't already
done so. And for the people who have
already done this, this is really
important. But also too, I feel like,
you know, moving a little bit away from
the governance portion of this and what
we're trying to do and creating creating
this framework is creating those
opportunities to have these discussions
with your family members if you haven't
yet. I had to do kind of the same thing
as well that this is a lot of us are the
people who are the cycle breakers. um we
are the ones who are saying that we are
going to move in a different direction.
We need to have more of that within our
communities and it's in as much as we're
working to provide access to this
medicine in a legal framework and a
medical framework,
not everyone needs to have the medicine.
But don't forget that you in your
conversations with people, you are the
medicine and it speaks through you. For
those of you who have had it, for those
of you who have been changed and
transformed through this medicine by the
education as was pointed out with L, um
the education is really important. Um,
and yes, according to Shane, you know,
this is also another opportunity to
have, you know, these networking with,
you know, your other like-minded
individuals. This is something where we
can all attack this problem of getting
the medicine out from different aspects.
Um and really I just want to encourage
everyone to continue listening to what
needs to be said or um also what needs
to be shared as far as like the
education the thing that you fear the
most I I feel is the thing that needs to
be done and that to me is in any aspect
of our lives whether it's you know I
also work in the film industry or
whether it's you know talking to my
child and it's like you know what was it
what is it that I'm going to share with
them and in that way That is really
honestly the work of the medicine andor
you as the medicine um to educate and to
share to as they say integrate right the
real work of the medicine is the
integration part when it comes to
working with other people and if we're
going to save this planet what it really
means though is that we're saving each
other and that's the community and
that's the conversations that we really
need to be having with one another. Um,
and so
I'll get off my soap box here, but um,
you know, we do have other,
um,
we do have other committees and, um, we
will be putting out more committee
meetings as we get, um, going with this.
Um we do have another board meeting um
when we're all coming together um to
discuss the different issues we've
discussed in the committees on January
16th. But there are other committees
that are be going to be working on and
you are all free to don't overwhelm
yourself but free to kind of go and peek
your head into those other committees as
well. We have end of life care research
and continuous improvement. I know
Dominic put um the links up in the chat
for you. Tell everybody, even if they're
just curious, if they're just listening
in and want to know what the discussion
is. Um because we it takes it really
does take a village and it takes all of
us to be able to understand what's going
on here.
Um okay.
All right.
Yes. So,
because
I I hate to say this, but like um
yeah, I'll go back and forth between the
fact that like this is work, state work,
government work, but then also standing
on my soap box and being kind of
preachy, but it's, you know, I just I
just feel like that we can all really
just do a lot more good work with each
other if we're um listening
really listening to what needs to to uh
and I feel like that's what will help
push the work through to get us as close
to
u completing what we need to get done as
a group as a whole in the next 11
months. So um thank you all for your
time. I appreciate it. Any other
thoughts? Please reach out on the um
psilocybin email link. you can address
it to the committee that you're
specifically having a question for. So
for example, if it's equity, access and
cultural considerations, it could be EAC
subject line um you know trainings,
facilities, whatever it is. Um that's
the way to reach out to all of us as a
group as a whole so we can have these
discussions when we are in our
committees or in our in the bigger board
meetings. So it's medical.silicybin
dooh.nm nm.gov.
So, thank you for your time. Um, have a
great night. I don't think I see anybody
else with their hand up. No. Okay. Thank
you for your time. I really appreciate
it.
>> Thank you everyone.
>> Thank you.